updated: 3/23 Chad McKell

ABOUT

Address 9500 Gilman Dr MC 0099

La Jolla, CA 92093-0099

Phone +1 661 289 4215
Email cmckell@ucsd.edu
Website chadmckell.com

Research I am a Ph.D. candidate at UC San Diego based in the Center for Visual Computing

and the Department of Music. I am primarily interested in geometry-based acoustic simulation and its applications in computer graphics, audio technology, and hearing science. Current research topics include variational methods for modeling fluid-structure interactions in musical instruments and human hearing; Kelvin transformations for handling obstacle and domain boundaries in acoustic wave simulations; and

parallelization of numerical integration schemes.

EDUCATION

9/19-	University of California San Diego, Ph.D. in Computer Music
	GPA: 4.0. Dissertation: Geometric Methods for Acoustic Simulation.
	Advisors: Albert Chern (CSE) and Miller Puckette (Music).
9/16-10/17	University of Edinburgh, M.S. in Acoustics and Music Technology
8/09-12/15	Wake Forest University, M.S. in Physics
6/02-8/09	Brigham Young University, B.S. in Biophysics

EMPLOYMENT

9/19-	University of California San Diego, Teaching Assistant/Researcher (Music)
8/21-3/22	Meta, Reality Labs Research, Research Intern/Student Researcher (Acoustics)
7/18-7/19	Applied Research in Acoustics, R&D Scientist (Acoustics)
5/18-5/18	Moog Music, Freelance Audio Software Developer (Audio DSP)
4/17-9/17	Lofelt, Freelance Acoustic Simulation Researcher (Acoustics)
10/14-8/16	J.P. Morgan/Neovest, Consulting Software Development Engineer in Test (QA)
8/12-12/12	University of North Carolina School of the Arts, Adjunct Instructor (Physics)
9/09-9/11	Wake Forest University, Teaching Assistant (Physics)
9/08-6/09	Brigham Young University, Tutorial Lab Assistant (Physics)
8/07-3/09	Brigham Young University, Research Assistant (Philosophy)

RESEARCH ACTIVITIES

9/19— University of California San Diego, Ph.D. Student/Candidate

La Jolla, California. Research areas: acoustics, applied mathematics. Develop geometric methods for simulating the acoustics of 3D environments, musical instruments, and human hearing. Research topics include virtual acoustics, sound simulation, hearing science, and differential geometry. Committee members: Albert Chern (co-chair, Computer Science and Engineering), Miller Puckette (co-chair, Music), Melvin Leok (Mathematics), Shahrokh Yadegari (Music), Stefan Bilbao (Music, University of Edinburgh), and Sebastian Prepeliță (Audio, Reality Labs Research at Meta).

RESEARCH ACTIVITIES CONT.

8/21–3/22 Meta, Reality Labs Research, Research Intern/Student Researcher

La Jolla, California. Research areas: acoustics, applied mathematics. Conducted computational acoustics research for virtual and augmented reality devices. Research topics included binaural audio, numerical simulation, parallel programming, and discrete complex analysis. Supervisor: Sebastian Prepeliță. Team Lead: Ravish Mehra.

7/18–7/19 Applied Research in Acoustics, R&D Scientist

Culpeper, Virginia. Research areas: acoustics, digital signal processing. Developed physics-based signal processing algorithms for naval sonar systems. Research topics included underwater acoustics, matched filtering, sparse estimation, and beamforming. Team Lead: Jonathan Botts.

1/17–8/17 University of Edinburgh, Master's Student

Edinburgh, Scotland. Research areas: acoustics, digital signal processing, elasto-dynamics. Developed physics-based numerical simulations of speech sounds and structural vibrations. Research topics included speech acoustics, modal synthesis, and finite-difference time-domain methods. Research was partially funded by Lofelt, a Berlin-based haptic feedback company acquired by Meta in 2022. Advisor: Stefan Bilbao.

1/10–9/13 Wake Forest University, Master's Student

Winston-Salem, North Carolina. Research areas: optics, fluid dynamics. Implemented transverse nanoparticle tracking in surface-isolated laser traps. Research topics included optical trapping, laser beam characterization, and fluid diffusion. Advisor: Keith Bonin.

8/07–8/09 Brigham Young University, Undergraduate Student

Provo, Utah. Research areas: biophysics, structural biology. Studied the effect of anesthetics on lipid bilayer structure using atomic force microscopy. Research topics included cellular membrane biology, vesicle fusion, and scanning probe microscopy. Advisor: David Busath.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

$\underline{\mathbf{UCSD}}$	
MUS 5	Sound in Time—TA. Spring 2020 (1 term).
MUS 6	Electronic Music—TA. Fall 2020 (1 term).
MUS 15	Popular Music: David Bowie—TA. Winter 2021 (1 term).
MUS 15	Popular Music: Video Game Music—TA. Winter 2020 (1 term).
MUS 171	Computer Music I—TA. Winter 2022 (1 term).
MUS 172	Computer Music II— <i>TA</i> . 2021–2022 (2 terms).
UNCSA	
SCI 1100	General Physics—Instructor. Fall 2012 (1 term).
$\overline{ ext{WFU}}$	
PHY 113	General Physics I (Mechanics)—TA. 2009–2011 (4 terms).
PHY 114	General Physics II (E&M)—Tutor. Fall 2010 (1 term).
DVII	
BYU PHSCS 105	Cananal Physics 1 (Machanics) Tuton 2008 2000 (2 tames)
	General Physics 1 (Mechanics)—Tutor. 2008–2009 (2 terms).
PHSCS 106	General Physics 2 (E&M)—Tutor. Winter 2009 (1 term).
PHSCS 121	Principles of Physics 1 (Mechanics)—Tutor. 2008–2009 (2 terms).
PHSCS 123	Principles of Physics 2 (Waves/Thermo)—Tutor. W/Sp 2009 (2 terms).
PHSCS 220	Principles of Physics 3 (E&M)—Tutor. W/Sp 2009 (2 terms)

PH.D. COURSEWORK

Computer Graphics I (Jürgen Schulze)
Computer Animation—audit (Steve Rotenberg)
Discrete Differential Geometry (Albert Chern)
Physical Simulation—audit (Steve Rotenberg)
Differential Geometry Research (Albert Chern)
Spatialization (Shahrokh Yadegari)
Deep Learning for Music Generation (Shlomo Dubnov)
Computational Acoustic Modeling (Tamara Smyth)
Digital Audio Processing (Tamara Smyth)
Analysis of Musical Sound (Miller Puckette)
Compositional Algorithms (Miller Puckette)
Advanced Projects in Computer Music (Puckette/Smyth)
Virtual Acoustics Research (Puckette/Smyth/Dubnov)
Differential Geometry Research (Miller Puckette)

PUBLICATIONS

Manuscripts in Progress

- (1) C. McKell, M. Nabizadeh, S. Wang, and A. Chern, "Wave simulations in infinite spacetime". Submission planned for June 2023.
- (2) C. McKell and S. Prepeliță. Topic: simulations of head-related transfer functions. Submission planned for 2023 or 2024.

Journal Articles

(3) C. McKell and K. Bonin, "Optical corral using a standing-wave Bessel beam," Journal of the Optical Society of America B, Vol. 35, No. 8, 1910–1920, 2018.

Conference Proceedings

(4) C. McKell, "Sonification of optically-ordered Brownian motion," In Proceedings of the International Computer Music Conference (ICMC), Utrecht, Netherlands, September 2016.

Master's Theses

- (5) C. McKell, Real-time physical modeling for haptic feedback rendering, Final Project Dissertation, University of Edinburgh, Acoustics and Audio Group, 2017. (Advisor: Stefan Bilbao).
- (6) C. McKell, Finite-difference simulations of speech with wall vibration losses, Special Project Dissertation, University of Edinburgh, Acoustics and Audio Group, 2017. (Advisor: Stefan Bilbao).
- (7) C. McKell, Confinement and tracking of Brownian particles in a Bessel beam standing wave, Master's Thesis, Wake Forest University, Department of Physics, 2015. (Advisor: Keith Bonin).

Technical Reports

(8) C. McKell, H. Conley, and D. Busath, "AFM study of structural changes in supported planar DPPC bilayers containing general anesthetic isoflurane," Brigham Young University, Paper 827, 2010.